JAMES MACIUKENAS, PH.D.

773-290-9947 | blueform@gmail.com www.linkedin.com/in/james-maciukenas

COMMUNICATOR | DEVELOPER | DESIGNER

SUMMARY

Communicator, Developer, and Designer with experience as strategic member of academic leadership teams and strong background in tailoring web, print, and event strategies to the needs of enrollment, fundraising and friend-raising. Team player with ability to serve as catalyst for innovative solutions to digital and print communication challenges. Establishes rapport and credibility with diverse groups and recognized for project management, analysis, and achieving goals. Solution-oriented while implementing constraint-based designed solutions that work.

- Communication
- Project Management

- Design Strategy
- Iterative Web Development

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Creative Cloud (Indesign, Photoshop, Illustrator, Dreamweaver, Premiere, Audition, Acrobat); Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint); HTML/CSS; Bootstrap; Wordpress Design and Development; Drupal; MailChimp; Facebook, Instagram, Twitter; Web-based Digital Signage Development; SQL; PHP; Mac + PC

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

INDIANA UNIVERSITY-BLOOMINGTON, Bloomington, IN Information Technology Services - Web Developer 2019-Present

Web development for the School of Public Health

DEPAUL UNIVERSITY, Chicago, IL

Information Services - Web Developer, Advancement 2019-Present

Web design and development for Advancement Office

Adjunct Instructor, 2019

- Online Facilitation Essentials (Online teaching training course for instructors)
- Web Design Tools Workshop (in-classroom)
- Introduction to Human-Computer Interaction (online)

ILLINOIS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY (IIT), Chicago, IL

Senior Web Development and Graphic Design Coordinator, 2011-2019

Integrated design thinking and UX research methods to deliver innovative and useful communication solutions for online and print audiences of College of Science (CoS).

- Designed and implemented web features using UX research, improving audience engagement with growth in unique pageviews year over year.
- Coordinated website development, training and maintenance, reducing technical support and downtime.
- Coordinated Content Management System transitions, managing stakeholder relationships for successful implementation.
- Conceived branding strategy building recognition for college with six unique departments with stakeholder audiences including prospective students, alumni, friends, and industry, which contributed to largest donation of over \$7 Million.

Adjunct Instructor (IIT), 2006-Present

 Developed curricula and taught graduate and undergraduate online and in-classroom courses in Web Design and Development, Document Design, Technical Communication, Publication Management, and Public Engagement for Scientists. Mentored student (Eric Galicia) on class project, resulting in winning Alan Alda's Flame Challenge. (2015)

Project and Communications Associate (IIT), 2007-2011

2019-Present

2019

2005-Present

• Completed web, print, and branding projects for CoS to raise awareness with prospective student, peer, alumni, and industry audiences.

Department Coordinator (IIT), 2005-2007

 Assisted Lewis Department of Humanities faculty and students with office tasks and technology support to improve efficiency.

PART-TIME CONSULTING EXPERIENCE

NEWCITY COMMUNICATIONS, INC., Chicago, IL

2015-Present

Web Developer and Print Magazine Production

• Supported Wordpress websites, increasing responsiveness and reducing security issues. Designed and prepared Newcity Magazine for production.

BUSINESS COMMUNICATION QUARTERLY (BCQ), Chicago, IL

2006-2013

Editorial Assistant

Assisted in preparation of manuscripts for on-time production and publication of BCQ.

NON-PROFIT VOLUNTEERING

AYSO YOUTH SOCCER, Evanston, IL Web Developer/ Assistant Coach

2016-2019

PIVOT ARTS, Chicago, IL

2014-2019

Creative Director/ Web Developer

• Designed promotional material and increased web security for arts organization.

ORDINARY PEOPLE INTERNATIONAL (OPI), NFP, Chicago, IL

2011-Present

Web Developer/ Creative Director

• Worked with non-profit organization, which assists underserved communities in Chicago.

EDUCATION

- Ph.D., Technical Communication, Illinois Institute of Technology (IIT), Chicago, IL Thesis: Toward Usability Guidelines for Single—Window Web Interfaces
- M.S., Technical Communication and Information Design, IIT, Chicago, IL Thesis: Toward a Digital Humanities Course: Open Source Software for Rapid Content Transition
- Graduate Certificate, Digital Technologies: Design Art Practice, Concordia University, Montreal, QC
- B.F.A., Industrial Design, University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, IL

AWARDS

- Service Award. IIT. (2017)
- Nominated for Staff Team Excellence Award. IIT. (2012-2013)
- Award of Excellence—Technical Art: Promotional and Informational Design. Society for Technical Communication, Chicago. Annual Communications Competition. (2009)
- Kudos Award. IIT. (2008)
- Dean's Excellence Award for Staff. IIT. (2008)
- Award of Excellence—Technical Art: Informational Materials Design. Society for Technical Communication, Chicago. Annual Communications Competition. (2008)
- Award of Merit—Technical Publications: Promotional Materials. Society for Technical Communication, Chicago. Annual Communications Competition. (2008)
- Teaching Assistantship, IIT. (2006-2008)
- Dean's Half-Tuition Scholarship. IIT. (2005-2006)
- Centre Interuniversitaire des Arts Médiatiques (CIAM) Graduate Certificate Student Research Funding Award, Concordia University, Montreal, Quebec. (2004-2005)